[music]
>> Welcome to Business Central Launch
Edition 2026 Wave 1.
Uh,
my name is Alexander Totovic and I will
start with this session introduction in
self-billing invoices.
Let's see what it's about.
Uh,
first I want to explain what exactly
self-billing is
because there are different
interpretation uh what is about. So,
what is self-billing in a case of this
new functionality? So, this is a process
where the customer, instead of the
vendor, create the invoice for goods or
service received. So, that means
customer will issue invoice on behalf of
his own vendor. That means customers
must have some specific agreement with
vendor, but if everything works fine, a
customer now can do it directly in a
Business Central.
In practice, how does it work? First,
user, as a customer, need to create
purchase order and to send this purchase
order to his vendor. Then, vendor will
deliver goods,
services, whatever is uh subject of this
uh transfer. After that, goods will be
received into the warehouse and from
this purchase order, customer will
automatically create a self-billing. And
after that, it will be sent to the
vendor and paid on the end. So, [snorts]
this is shortly the process what is
about self-billing.
So, the main business values
we will reduce operational workload and
faster processing.
So, earlier,
you could do partially, but you had to
do a lot of uh steps manually and plus,
we will improve completely accuracy and
compliance because earlier, you minimum
need to you need to have some specific
customization how to prepare specific uh
invoice sales invoice connected on a
purchase order. You needed some
configuration there. So, now everything
is
>> [snorts]
>> uh enabled by default, so you can easily
start and use it.
>> [gasps]
>> Setup is not so complicated. In general,
you will find on a
uh invoicing fast tab on a vendor card,
self-billing agreement
uh boolean field. You just need to
enable it. So, from the moment when you
enable it, you will automatically create
self-billing invoices from purchase
order or purchase invoice for this
vendor. So, you do not need to expect
this invoice from your vendor. So, only
this one setup field.
>> [snorts]
>> What else is necessary? You need to go
to purchase and payable setup and to
create posted self-billing invoice
number series.
Uh this number series will be used as
external document number because now you
need to create your vendor uh sales
invoice on behalf of them and that means
you need to have some
uh a number of series for that.
After that, when you configure
everything, you just need to start with
your purchase invoice or purchase order,
whatever you decide regardless, and your
vendor invoice number will be populated
automatically based on this number
series. You don't need to enter
uh this external document number.
One thing before that, before you start,
you need to choose uh specific uh
report. So, you need to go to report
selection, purchase, and to select
self-billing invoice type.
Now, I will show you how you can do it
in a demo.
I already mentioned you need to open
vendor card.
I already configured this one vendor
50,000. So, if you look here invoicing,
self-billing agreement is a new field
and I already marked it. So, that means
from this moment, I don't need to create
manually sales invoices from this
customer.
Okay.
Um
what else I need to do? I need to go to
purchase and payable setup.
And to create posted sales billing
invoices number series.
And the last
report selection
for
purchase
and you will find the last new option
self-billing invoice.
You have new report
413 self-billing invoice and this is
what system will use.
So, now when I start with a
purchase invoice, for example,
and create new one,
if I use this vendor,
you will see vendor invoice number is
disabled because this vendor is already
planned to be used as a uh for
self-billing invoicing. So, now only
what I need to do is to select one of
items to close this.
Okay, I will purchase
one
chair
and post it.
Okay. Now, when I open
posted document,
I can
use print send
and you will see I have now a report
layout by default self-billing invoice.
If I open and preview it,
you will see even this is from purchase
invoice, you have now printout you can
use as your inbound invoice from your
vendor.
So, this is
named as a self-billing invoice. So, you
have your regular number uh series for
your uh posted purchase invoices. So,
you have here now your vendor
information.
Now, you are a customer.
All other details are here. So,
everything what you purchased,
everything is fine. So, all important
information are filled in the same as
any sales invoice will be exposed here.
So, you can print it, you can use it
without any problem.
Even if this is in a background, this is
posted purchase invoice, it will be
showed as a sales invoice.
The same situation is if you choose a
purchase order. I will not post, I will
just create new one
just to show how it works.
Okay, you will see vendor invoice number
is now disabled. And again, you can just
choose one of options [snorts] and you
can post. Result will be absolutely the
same.
So, this is about how system is worked.
In general, this is not complicated, but
it will help a lot, especially if you
have big distributors and uh you want to
have self-billing invoice. Earlier, you
needed some customization, so now it can
go much easier. What I want to emphasize
in this moment. Currently, we deliver
this functionality, so this is uh
available from uh 26 release wave 1, but
we do not have covered electronic
invoicing basing on self-billing
invoice. So, this is something what we
plan to deliver uh next release because
first we want to get the feedback how it
works. So, if everything is okay for
you, if uh there is no any issue how it
works, we will deliver electronic
invoicing based on this functionality in
next release.
So, now before I close this session, I
just want to emphasize all these links,
important links you can follow, you can
track
uh
LinkedIn as well and our YouTube
channel.
So, please go there and you can find a
lot of interesting content.
So, now thank you for joining this
session in Business Central Launch
Edition.